{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "While serving as a Senator, this man drafted the Violence Against Women Act and oversaw Robert Bork’s Supreme Court confirmation hearing as chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee. This man was accused of plagiarizing a speech by Labour politician Neil Kinnock during his 1988 Presidential run. In another campaign, this man called a “lecture on embassy security” a “bunch of malarkey” in a debate with 2012 Paul Ryan. For ten points, name this current Vice President of the United States.",
      "answer": "Joseph Robinette “Joe” Biden"
    },
    {
      "question": "Heinrich Kreutz names a group of these objects, whose members include Ikeya-Seki. The Giotto probe observes these objects and is named because the painter Giotto incorporated one of these objects into his Adoration of the Magi. The destruction of one of these objects named Shoemaker-Levy 9 was observed in 1994. Long period ones may originate from the Oort Cloud. Another of these objects last visited earth in 1986 and will return in 2061. For ten points, name these astronomical objects, one of which is named for Edmond Halley.",
      "answer": "comets"
    },
    {
      "question": "One man who worked for this organization was possibly assassinated by the ARENA party in El Salvador. Another man from this organization, Aloysius Stepinac, was jailed for feuding with Joseph Tito. In addition to the aforementioned Oscar Romero, another assassination target from this organization was targeted in the Bojinka plot by the Grey Wolves and Mehmed Ali Agca [AH-jah]. That person was of Polish descent and took his name from his predecessor, who had died after 33 days in office. For ten points, name this organization formerly led by John Paul II.",
      "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1757, tens of thousands of people who had recently performed this action died when a group led by Qa’dan al-Faiz raided their caravan. Unlike a similar action, this action must be done during Dhu al-Hijjah. This action includes a series of rituals, including drinking from the Zamzam Well, the symbolic stoning of the devil, and circling the Kaaba seven times. For ten points, name this pillar of Islam that requires Muslims to, at least once in a lifetime, undertake a pilgrimage to Mecca.",
      "answer": "Hajj"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this film, a character known as the “Little Colonel” is hospitalized and meets Elsie. An attack on the Cameron family is thwarted in this film, whose character of Austin Stoneman was inspired by Thaddeus Stevens. Like in Apocalypse Now, “The Ride of the Valkyries” is played during a charge in this film. Thomas Dixon, the author of its source material, arranged it to be screened at the White House for Woodrow Wilson. For ten points, name this 1915 D.W. Griffith film that glorified the Ku Klax Klan.",
      "answer": [
        "The Birth of a Nation",
        "The Clansman"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Abraham Woodhull and Robert Townsend performed this action after being recruited by Benjamin Tallmadge. While performing this action, Hercules Mulligan used his slave Cato as a courier. John Champe defected to the British army while performing this action, and while working for the British in London, Edward Bancroft performed this action. The Culper Ring was created to perform this action, whose perpetrators were considered illegal combatants. For ten points, name this wartime act for which Nathan Hale was hanged.",
      "answer": [
        "spying for the United States",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was foreshadowed by a poem that described rolled up tube socks and noted “I’m ready to let you go.” A Jordan Clarkson full-court assist punctuated this event, the subject of an eBay auction of a bag of air that reached $15,000 before it was pulled. This event took place on the same day that Golden State won its 73rd game. For ten points, name this April 2016 event which featured 50 field goal attempts, 60 points, and the conclusion “Mamba out” from a 20-year veteran of the L.A. Lakers.",
      "answer": [
        "Kobe Bryant’s final NBA game or Kobe Bryant’s retirement",
        "first and/or last name"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, the Trail of the Eagles’ Nests is a series of 25 castles built by this country’s only king to be styled “the Great.” This country’s first Christian ruler, Mieszko I, conquered Mazovia for the Piast dynasty, a ruling house that ended after the death of the aforementioned Casimir the Great. For ten points, name this European country that joined in a 17th century commonwealth with Lithuania and maintained dual capitals at Vilnius and Krakow.",
      "answer": "Poland"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A reduction of the pays d’en haut [pay den hoh] contributed to this conflict. An attack on a wagon train led to the Devil’s Hole Massacre in this conflict, during which Jeffrey Amherst used smallpox infected blankets as a weapon during the siege of Fort Pitt. The battles of both Bushy and Bloody Run took place in this conflict, which opened with the siege of Fort Detroit. For ten points, name this Great Lakes-area rebellion that followed the French and Indian War, as an Ottawa chieftain tried to push the British out.",
        "answer": "Pontiac’s War or Rebellion, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A popular misconception is that Pontiac’s War led to this piece of British legislature, which controversially forbade settlement west of the Appalachians and angered the colonists.",
        "answer": "Proclamation of 1763"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jeff Bagwell broke his hand the day before this event began. Sonia Sotomayor’s injunction ended this event, which was directed by Donald Fehr. Tony Gwynn was batting .394 when this event began, costing him a chance to become the first .400 hitter since Ted Williams. Commissioner Bud Selig was heavily criticized for his actions during this event, though fans blamed both sides for their greed in negotiations. For ten points, name this 1994-95 labor stoppage that cancelled a World Series.",
        "answer": [
          "1994-95 Major League Baseball or MLB strike",
          "1994 and/or 1995 with the answer"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When the 1994 season was shut down, this team’s 74-40 record was the best in baseball. In 2004, this team moved south, becoming the Washington Nationals and ending the MLB mascot career of Youppi.",
        "answer": [
          "Montreal Expos",
          "either",
          "both names"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was once licked awake by a lion after an encounter with another conqueror at Taxila, which was interpreted as a sign that he would one day be king. Megasthenes visited the empire of this ruler, whose war elephants at the Battle of Ipsus led to the victory of Seleucus. This ruler’s advisor Chanakya wrote the Arthashastra. This ruler’s son Bindusara inherited his empire, which was founded after his defeat of the Nanda Empire. For ten points, name this ruler, the grandfather of Ashoka, who founded the Mauryan Empire.",
        "answer": [
          "Chandragupta Maurya",
          "Sandrocottos",
          "Androcottus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In his last days, Chandragupta converted to what religion, which holds that Mahavira is the last tirthankara?",
        "answer": "Jainism"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This initiative received aid from foreign intelligence in Operation Charly. Court judges were impeded from ruling against this initiative via Operation Silence, and MIR leaders Edgardo Enriquez and Jorge Fuentes were attacked in this initiative. DINA contributed greatly to this operation, which forced Martin Almada to listen to the torture of his wife over telephone. Archives of Terror in Asuncion recorded the actions of this initiative, which was spearheaded by Augusto Pinochet. For ten points, name this CIA-backed cleanup of political enemies and communists in South American countries.",
        "answer": "Operation Condor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Condor was supported by this long time dictator of Paraguay, who renamed Ciudad del Este in his own honor.",
        "answer": "Alfredo Stroessner"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The ships Goeben and Breslau were able to find haven in this nation’s waters. The Treaty of Erzincan helped end one conflict that this nation entered after the Battle of Odessa. This nation, which lost control of Jerusalem to Edmund Allenby, was led by the Pashas Enver and Talaat. The Treaties of Sevres and Lausanne brought an end to this empire. It faced a revolt in the Hejaz led by T.E. Lawrence and it perpetrated the Armenian Genocide. For ten points, name this empire that joined with the Central Powers in World War I, then dissolved after its defeat.",
        "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ottoman Empire had earlier attempted to curb its decline with this series of reforms that removed the millet system. This term literally means “reorganization.”",
        "answer": "Tanzimat"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man promulgated the Wantage legal code. The battle of Maldon took place under this monarch, whose brother was killed by Queen Elfrida. Thorkell the Tall attacked this monarch’s kingdom, and this monarch unwisely ordered the St. Brices Day Massacre. This monarch was the father of both Edward the Confessor and Edmund Ironsides. The Danegeld tributes were controversially paid by, for ten points, what monarch whose epithet actually means he was poorly advised?",
        "answer": "Aethelred the Unready or Aethelred II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aethelred’s son, Edmund Ironsides, was deposed by this “great” Scandinavian ruler, who won the Battle of Assandun.",
        "answer": "Canute the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One party formed for this election year was comprised of remnants of the earlier Opposition party. Two minor parties in this election included the People’s Party and Liberty Party, the latter of which nominated Gerrit Smith. One party carried only Missouri in this year after it nominated the formulator of the Freeport Doctrine, and John Bell Hood’s ticket carried only 3 states for the Constitutional Union Party. For ten points, name this presidential election year in which four parties split the electoral college, allowing the Republican Abraham Lincoln to take the White House.",
        "answer": "Election of 1860"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Southern Democratic candidate, a future Confederate commander who led a reserve force at Shiloh, carried the South and Maryland in the 1860 election.",
        "answer": "John Breckinridge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man disparaged the “French trash” of imitating croaking frogs in an oratorio he wrote with librettist Gottfried van Swieten. The second movement of one of his works is a theme-and-variations on a melody he wrote for Emperor Francis II that eventually became the Deutschlandlied. This composer of the Erdody Quartets and The Seasons ended another work with musicians leaving one by one. For ten points, what “father of the string quartet” wrote the Farewell Symphony?",
        "answer": "Joseph Haydn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Haydn wrote the Farewell Symphony to convince his patron, this Hungarian prince, to give his musicians a vacation.",
        "answer": "Prince Nikolaus Esterhazy"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Millard Fillmore...",
      "prompt": "Name the millard fillmore......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "was from which state, where he helped found the University of Buffalo?",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "authorized the Treaty of Kanagawa with what foreign country?",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "represented which political party while President?",
          "answer": "Whig Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "lost the 1856 election running under what anti-Catholic party?",
          "answer": "Know Nothing Party or Native American Party Compromise of 1850"
        },
        {
          "question": "supported which multi-faceted agreement that included the admission of California as a free state?",
          "answer": "Compromise of 1850"
        },
        {
          "question": "is the namesake of the city of Fillmore, the first capital of which territory?",
          "answer": "Utah Territory"
        },
        {
          "question": "denied pleas from which exiled Hungarian leader to recognize the independence of Hungary?",
          "answer": [
            "Lajos Kossuth",
            "names in either order"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "had a personal audience with which long-reigning pope after his presidency?",
          "answer": [
            "Pius IX",
            "Pio Nono"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE EASTERN FRONT OF WORLD WAR II",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about THE EASTERN FRONT OF WORLD WAR II...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Eastern European Allied nation Germany fought on that front?",
          "answer": [
            "U.S.S.R.",
            "the Soviet Union"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "then-name of the city targeted by an 872-day siege, now known as St. Petersburg?",
          "answer": "Leningrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "German operation that called for an invasion of the U.S.S.R.?",
          "answer": "Operation Barbarossa"
        },
        {
          "question": "victorious Soviet commander at the Battle of Stalingrad?",
          "answer": "Georgy Konstantinovich Zhukov"
        },
        {
          "question": "large tank battle that the Germans called Operation Citadel?",
          "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
        },
        {
          "question": "medium-sized German tank first deployed in that battle that could not match Soviet T-34s?",
          "answer": "Panther"
        },
        {
          "question": "legendary Soviet sniper who tallied more than 200 kills at Stalingrad?",
          "answer": "Vasily Grigoryevich Zaytsev"
        },
        {
          "question": "codename given to the German operation that tried to envelop Moscow?",
          "answer": "Operation Typhoon"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HISTORY OF LANGUAGES",
      "prompt": "In linguistic history, name...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the subfamily of languages including Spanish, French, and other languages derived from Latin.",
          "answer": "Romance languages"
        },
        {
          "question": "the language that experienced a medieval Great Vowel Shift, as seen in the works of Chaucer.",
          "answer": "English"
        },
        {
          "question": "either of the two countries whose national tongue is a form of Gaelic.",
          "answer": [
            "Scotland",
            "the Republic of Ireland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "the people of northern Spain whose language predates the Indo-European languages of Western Europe.",
          "answer": "Basque"
        },
        {
          "question": "the law that describes how stop consonants evolved from Proto-Indo-European into Proto-Germanic.",
          "answer": "Grimm’s Law"
        },
        {
          "question": "the writing system for Mycenaean Greek deciphered by Michael Ventris.",
          "answer": "Linear B"
        },
        {
          "question": "the French archaeologist who deciphered the Rosetta Stone.",
          "answer": "Jean-Francois Champollion"
        },
        {
          "question": "the constructed language of Johann Schleyer that was overshadowed by Esperanto.",
          "answer": "Volapu¨k"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to legend, one of these people successfully carried water in a sieve to prove her innocence. They were responsible for the preparation of mola salsa, a mixture of flour and salt, that was used in every official (20 pts)",
        "sacrifice. According to Zosimus’s Historia Nova, the last of these people cursed Stilicho’s wife Serena for desecrating the temple of Rhea Silvia. These people took a vow of (10 pts)",
        "chastity for 30 years, that if broken, led to the violator being buried alive in the Campus Sceleratus. One of the chief duties of these people was to keep the sacred fire of the deity they served burning. For ten points, name these priestesses of the Roman goddess of the hearth."
      ],
      "answer": "Vestal Virgins"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One work by the sculptor consists of a circular stone table ringed by twelve hourglass- shaped seats. That piece is part of an ensemble that also includes a tower consisting of seventeen-and-a-half stacked (20 pts)",
        "rhomboids, built to commemorate World War I veterans at Targu Jiu. He also created an elongated bronze sculpture which was the subject of a (10 pts)",
        "court case after American customs officials initially refused to categorize it as art. For ten points, name this abstract Romanian sculptor of Endless Column and Bird In Space."
      ],
      "answer": "Constantin Brˆancusi , but be lenient with phonetic pronunciations"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This case was used as precedent during D’Emden v. Pedder, which helped flesh out the Australian Constitution. The word “expressly” greatly affected this case’s ruling, which established the implied powers of Congress to enforce (20 pts)",
        "expressed powers, citing Hamilton’s criteria. John Marshall invoked the “necessary and proper” clause in this case, whose ruling found that the “power to (10 pts)",
        "tax is the power to destroy”. For ten points, name this 1819 Supreme Court case that deemed it unconstitutional for a state to tax the Second Bank of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "McCulloch v. Maryland",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s party rose to power after a series of protests against water privatization in the city of Cochabamba. Shortly after being inaugurated, this leader of the Movement for Socialism adopted a (20 pts)",
        "“Coca yes, Cocaine no!” farming policy in opposition to American interests. In February 2016, this successor of Eduardo Rodriguez lost a referendum to extend his term limits to allow him to run again in 2020. In 2013, this leader’s (10 pts)",
        "flight out of Moscow was grounded in Vienna after it was suspected that his plane contained Edward Snowden. For ten points, name this current President of Bolivia."
      ],
      "answer": "Evo Morales"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Suka Wars were fought throughout these locations. During a 1953 incident, Janis Mendriks was killed when soldiers fired into a crowd at one of these institutions. Naftaly Frenkel established a system of (20 pts)",
        "rations used at these locations. According to Anne Applebaum, two people who escaped one of these institutions invited a chef along with them so he could be used as food. The first one of these locations opened in 1921 on the (10 pts)",
        "Solovetsky Islands. The town of Vorkuta was created to support, for ten points, what Soviet prison camps?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "gulags",
        "Soviet labor camps"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After the passing of a law named for this region, governor Guy Carleton was accused of attempting to entrench Catholicism here. Richard Montgomery and (20 pts)",
        "Benedict Arnold led a failed attempt to capture this region that prompted John Burgoyne’s Hudson River campaign. In a 1759 battle in this region, both the (10 pts)",
        "Marquis de Montcalm and James Wolfe were killed. This region was captured by the British in the Seven Years War after a victory at the Plains of Abraham. For ten points, name this region, a modern day French-speaking Canadian province."
      ],
      "answer": "Quebec"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Charles Rose and John Bly were the only people executed for their roles in this event. James Bowdoin, who took over as Governor for the ill John Hancock, responded brutally to this event and promptly lost the next gubernatorial election to Hancock. (20 pts)",
        "Samuel Adams briefly considered suspending habeas corpus during this event, in which the “Regulators” formed an (10 pts)",
        "anti-tax militia that shut down courts and tried to take the Springfield Armory. For ten points, name this 1786 rebellion of Massachusetts farmers that illustrated the weakness of the Articles of Confederation."
      ],
      "answer": "Shays’ Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man ended Quintus Sertorius’ revolt, and it took this man just a few months to end a wave of piracy after he was given a navy by the Lex (20 pts)",
        "Gabinia. This man won a minor victory at the Battle of Dyrrhachium, about a month before he was forced into fighting against the Populares in Greece. Those battles were fought as this man faced against a former (10 pts)",
        "ally, who had joined this man in an alliance with Marcus Licinius Crassus. For ten points, name this member of the First Triumvirate whose loss at Pharsalus allowed Julius Caesar to win the Roman Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Pompey the Great or Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus"
    }
  ]
}